Donald B. Miller Collection
Onondaga Community College
Donald B. Miller Collection
1954 - 2011
The Donald B. Miller collection contains material donated to the Onondaga Community College archives by OCC music professor Dr. Donald B. Miller. It includes music written by Donald Miller, materials from his years as a music professor at Onondaga Community College, and his research material on composer Kirke Mechem, the subject of his doctoral dissertation.
6 linear feet
Onondaga Community College
4585 W Seneca Turnpike Syracuse, NY 13215
This collection is open to researchers without restriction.
Dr. Donald B. Miller was a music professor at Onondaga Community College from 1971 to 1998, and worked part time at the college until 2000. Dr. Miller composed and arranged many works of music, which have been and continue to be performed around the world. Among the many compositions, the hymn "Here Rests in Honored Glory" and "Finger Lakes Suite" are two of his well known works. Dr. Miller received his PhD in 1981 at the University of Southern California, where he wrote his dissertation on the composer Kirke Mechem.
Miller, Donald B., 1937-; VHS; compact discs; sheet music; reviews (documents); catalogs (documents); certificates; color photographs; scores; Mechem, Kirke; black-and-white photographs; Onondaga Community College; Choral singing; Patriotic music--United States; Soldiers--Hymns; Composition (Music); Guitar--Studies and exercises; Veterans; Christmas music--Juvenile sound recordings; audiocassettes; speeches (documents); long-playing records; interviews; open reel audiotapes; correspondence; doctoral dissertations
The collection comprises archival materials relating to the musical career of Donald B. Miller. The main categories of the collection include: Guitar Ensemble Series, Onondaga Community College Choral European Tour, "Here Rests in Honored Glory" material, "Finger Lakes Suite" material, "Christopher the Christmas Tree" material, 14 other original scores by Donald Miller, and his material on Kirke Mechem, used to write his PhD thesis. Each series is organized into narrower subseries and then arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Guitar Ensemble Series - This series includes material relating to guitar instruction books written by Donald B. Miller and published by Mel Bay. Materials include the music, and related materials pertaining to the publication, performance and use of the series. Date coverage 2000-2011.
Series 2: Onondaga Community College Choral European Tour - This series contains the information relating to a college tour lead by Donald Miller to the Netherlands. It includes publicity, photographs, correspondence and awards related to the trip. Date coverage 1973.
Series 3: "Here Rests in Honored Glory" - This series contains information on the hymn that Donald Miller wrote to honor those who have served in the military. This material includes the musical scores, honors, publicity, performance information, and recordings of the hymn. Dates coverage 1984-2019.
Series 4: "Finger Lakes Suite" - This archives includes the development of this suite of music, performance information, publicity, musical scores and recordings. Dates coverage 1965-1992.
Series 5: "Christopher the Christmas Tree" - This series includes information on the book and accompanied music that comprises "Christopher the Christmas Tree" project. It includes the musical score, the book drafts, the publicity and publishing information. Date coverage 1988-2000.
Series 6-18, 21: Other Original Works by Donald B. Miller - Fourteen other original works are included in this series, and include the musical scores written by Donald B. Miller. Date coverage 1985-2009, undated.
Series 19: PhD Materials on Kirke Mechem - This archives includes articles, music, interviews, newspaper clippings, recordings, and correspondence about composer Kirke Mechem, who's music was the subject of Donald B. Millers PhD dissertation. Date coverage 1968-1983.
Series 20: Miscellaneous - Miscellaneous material about the life and work of Donald B. Miller, including newspaper clippings, articles and recordings by and about Dr. Miller. Date coverage 1959-1983.
- 1: Guitar Ensemble Series by Don Miller, 2000 - 2002; Miller, Donald B., 1937-; Donald Miller Guitar Ensemble Series includes 6 books that offer level one guitar quartet settings of themes from various musical periods, intended for multiple guitars for use in classroom or on the recital stage. In addition, there is a booklet containing examples from the 6 books, called the New Frontier. These books are published by Mel Bay Publications, Inc. This collection also includes recordings, awards, correspondence and other material relating to the production of this series.
  - Guitar Ensemble Volumes, 2000 - 2001
    - Baroque Music, 2001 (Box-folder MIL1-1)
    - Christmas Book, 2000 (Box-folder MIL1-2)
    - Music From Around the World, 2002 (Box-folder MIL1-3)
    - Music of the Hispanic World, 2002 (Box-folder MIL1-4)
    - Music of the Masters, 2000 (Box-folder MIL1-5)
    - Music of the Renaissance, 2001 (Box-folder MIL1-6)
    - The New Frontier - Sheet music, 2003 (Box-folder MIL1-6A)
  - Other Mel Bay Publications, 2000 - 2009
    - "Hallelujah Chorus" from Messiah by George Frederich Handel, arranged by Don Miller, 2000 (Box-folder MIL1-7)
    - "Magnificat" by Charles Theodore Pachelbel, transcribed by Donald Miller, 2005 (Box-folder MIL1-8)
    - "Music From Around the World", books 1-3 for violin 1 & 2 with piano accompaniment, by Donald Miller, 2009 (Box-folder MIL1-9)
  - Miscellaneous, 2005
    - Correspondence, 2000 - 2005 (Box-folder MIL1-10)
  - Mel Bay Catalogs, 2000 - 2002
    - Catalogs containing works by Donald B. Miller, 2000 - 2002 (Box-folder MIL1-11)
  - Photographs, 2000
    - Guitar emsembles, 2000 (Box-folder MIL1-12)
  - Reviews, 2002 - 2006
    - Reviews of work by Donald B. Miller, 2002 - 2006 (Box-folder MIL1-13)
  - Workshops, Performance Programs, 2001 - 2011
    - Workshops and Performances featuring Donald B. Miller, 2001 - 2011 (Box-folder MIL1-14)
  - Award Certificates, 2002 - 2004
    - Certificates of Appreciation, 2002 - 2004 (Box-folder MIL1-15)
  - Performance Recordings, 2003
    - VHS Tape - Donald Miller Guitar Ensemble Series - The New Frontier, 2003 (Box-folder MIL1-16)
    - CD - Donald Miller Guitar Ensemble Series, 2003 (Box-folder MIL1-17)
- 2: Onondaga Community College Choral Ensemble European Tour, 1973; Onondaga Community College was the first two-year school from the United States to perform in the International Koorfestival in the Netherlands. The Choir placed 3rd out of sixty-eight choirs.
  - Commemorative Placques, 1973
    - Metal placque, June, 1973 (Box-folder MIL5-1)
    - Ceramic wall placque, 1973 (Box-folder MIL5-1A)
  - Concert Poster - in Dutch, June, 1973 (Box MIL2)
  - Concert Photographs, June 19, 1973 (Box-folder MIL5-2)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder MIL1-18)
  - Programs, June 7, 1973 (Box-folder MIL1-19)
  - Reviews, 1973 (Box-folder MIL1-20)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973 (Box-folder MIL1-21)
- 3: "Here Rests in Honored Glory" by Don Miller, 1984 - 2010; Miller, Donald B., 1937-; The original piece by Donald B. Miller, titled "Here Rests in Honored Glory", is based on the inscription on the Tomb of the Unknown Soldier at Arlington National Cemetery outside of Washington, D.C. It is scored for a chorus, several brass instruments, timpani, and organ. This collection of materials relates to Professor Miller’s composition and the subsequent honors that both it and he have received.
  - "Here Rests in Honored Glory" original score, 1984
    - Conductor's Score - original key, January 1, 1984 (Box-folder MIL3-1)
    - "Here Rests in Honored Glory" Instrumental Parts, 1984 (Box-folder MIL3-2)
    - "Here Rests in Honored Glory" sheet music, 1st, 2nd and 3rd editions, Mark Foster Music Co., 1986 (Box-folder MIL3-3)
  - Performance Programs and miscellaneous material, 1984 - 2010
    - Premiere Performance - Cathedral of the Immaculate Conception, Syracuse, NY, May, 1984 (Box-folder MIL3-4)
    - Performance Programs - various locations, 1984 - 2001 (Box-folder MIL3-5)
    - 38th Annual Veterans Day National Ceremony, Washington, DC publicity material, photographs, November, 1991 (Box-folder MIL3-8)
  - Awards and Honors, 1991 - 2019
    - Freedom Foundation Award - George Washington Honor Medal nominations and awards material, 2009 (Box-folder MIL3-6)
    - Veterans of the Vietnam War official hymn honor printed material, 1991 (Box-folder MIL3-7)
    - Paralyzed Veterans of America official hymn honor printed material, 1991 (Box-folder MIL3-7)
    - Designation - New York State's Official Hymn of Rememberance, 2017 - 2019 (Box-folder MIL 3-14)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1994 - 2019 (Box-folder MIL3-9, Box-folder MIL 3-14)
  - Correspondence, 1984 - 1991 and 2016 - 2019 (Box-folder MIL3-10, Box-folder MIL 3-14)
  - Recording Session, 2005
    - Correspondence, 2005 (Box-folder MIL3-11)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2005 (Box-folder MIL3-11)
  - Television coverage, undated
    - VHS tape, undated (Box-folder MIL3-12)
  - Performance Recordings, 2005
    - "Here Rests in Honored Glory" CD, 2005 (Box-folder MIL3-13)
    - "Sounds of America" CD, 1982 (Box-folder MIL3-13)
  - Donald Miller's notes on composition of "Here Rests in Honored Glory", 2019 (Box-folder MIL 3-14)
- 4: "Finger Lakes Suite" original score by Don Miller, 1989; Miller, Donald B., 1937-; The Finger Lakes Suite is an original orchestral composition by Donald B. Miller, highlighting the beauty of the Finger Lakes Region in Central New York. The work debuted on July 19, 1989 in Skaneateles, New York by the Syracuse Symphony Orchestra, under the direction of Neil Gittleman. The Suite consists of three movements, Lake Country Images, A Distant Dream and A Celebration of the Earth's Bounty. Each movement is connected by a brief repeating section, The Erie Canal Promenade, that links the three movements.Included in this series is the musical work Birches, which was the original model for the Finger Lakes Suite.
  - "Birches" original manuscript, 1965 (Box-folder MIL5-3)
  - "Finger Lakes Suite", 1989 (Box-folder MIL4-2)
    - First Draft of "Finger Lakes Suite", 1988 (Box-folder MIL4-3)
    - Handwritten reworking of orchestration for "Finger Lakes Suite", undated (Box-folder MIL4-4)
    - Revisions for "Finger Lakes Suite", 1988 (Box-folder MIL4-5)
    - Conductors copy - Neal Gittleman,Syracuse Symphony Orchestra, 1989 (Box-folder MIL4-6)
    - Program notes, 1989 (Box-folder MIL4-7)
    - DVD Recording of Finger Lakes Suite, 1990 (Box-folder MIL4-8)
    - Correspondance, 1988 (Box-folder MIL4-9)
    - Reviews, 1991 (Box-folder MIL4-10)
    - Ithaca College video production correspondence, catalogs, VHS tape, 1989 - 1992 (Box-folder MIL4-11)
    - Concert Programs, 1989 - 2011 (Box-folder MIL4-12)
    - Publicity/Press fliers and correspondence, 1989 - 1999 (Box-folder MIL4-13)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1989 (Box-folder MIL4-14)
    - Poster - Premier Performance by Syracuse Symphony Orchestra, 1989 (Box-folder MIL5-4)
    - Original score in pencil, 1989 (Box-folder MIL5-5)
- 5: "Christopher the Christmas Tree" original score by Don Miller, 1988 - 1999; The archives of "Christopher the Christmas Tree", chronicles the creation of a book and accompanying musical cassette tape/CD. The project was a collaboration between the story's author Nancy Poole, the composer Donald B. MIller and illustrator Christie L. Stahl Burghdorf. The archives includes the original scores of the 5 songs included in the project, the drafts and final copies of the text and illustrations used for the book. The archives also includes photographs, financial and business records, and correspondence associated with all phases of the creation and publication of the project.
  - Story Synopsis, undated (Box-folder MIL1-22)
  - Song Sheet, undated (Box-folder MIL1-23)
  - Musical Score - Original and Published, 1989 - 1993
    - "Christopher the Christmas Tree" score, 1989 (Box-folder MIL1-24)
    - "Reach for the Stars" score, 1989 (Box-folder MIL1-24)
    - "Silent Star, Silent Sky" score, 1993 (Box-folder MIL1-25)
    - "To Be Me" score, 1989 (Box-folder MIL1-26)
  - Story Illustrations, undated
    - Illustrations by Christie L. Stahl Burghdorf, undated (Box-folder MIL1-27)
    - Illustration by Douglas McCarthy, Warner Brothers Animation, 1992 (Box-folder MIL1-28)
  - Review of Project - by Bruce Coville, 1997 (Box-folder MIL1-29)
  - Book "Christopher the Christmas Tree" documents, undated
    - First draft of book and correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-30)
    - Final Draft, 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-31)
    - Published Book/ CD, 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-32)
    - ISBN number application, 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-39)
  - Correspondence, 1988 - 1997 (Box-folder MIL1-33)
  - Trademark application, 1999 - 2000 (Box-folder MIL1-34)
  - Financial documents, 1996 - 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-35)
  - Grass Lake Publishing documents, 1999 (MIL1-36)
  - Photographs - recording session, undated (Box-folder MIL1-37)
  - Copyright documents, 1994 - 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-38)
  - Recording, 199u
    - Cassette tape - final mix, undated (Box-folder MIL1-40)
    - 1/4' tape, 7 1/2 IPS (full track), undated (Box-folder MIL1-40)
  - Publicity, 1999 (Box-folder MIL1-41)
- 6: "It's So Sweet" by Donald Miller, undated; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Conductor's score, arrangement for stage band by Steve Frank, undated (Box-folder MIL4-15)
- 7: "Charconne" by Don Miller, undated; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original Score in Pencil, undated (Box-folder MIL4-16)
  - Chaconne for Strings, undated (Box-folder MIL4-17)
- 8: "Sontantina" by Don Miller, undated; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original Score, undated (Box-folder MIL4-18)
- 9: "Dawn Bears the Sun" by Don Miller, undated; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original Score with pencil notes, undated (Box-folder MIL4-19)
  - Score, undated (Box-folder MIL4-20)
- 10: "Sing Along on this Day" by Don Miller, undated; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original Score, undated (Box-folder MIL4-21)
  - Score - Final Proof, undated (Box-folder MIL4-21)
- 11: "Star Songs" by Don Miller, 1995; Miller, Donald B., 1937-; "Star Songs" is a collection of four songs, including "Star Child", To Be Me", "Silent Star, Silent Sky" and "Reach for a Star".
  - Score, April, 1995 (Box-folder MIL4-22)
- 12: "Suite" by Don Miller, September, 2004; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Score for 2 clarinets, or 2 guitars, or 2 vibraphones, or 1 vibe & 1 marimba, September, 2004 (Box-folder MIL4-23)
- 13: "The Hebrew Children" arrangement by Don Miller, undated, 1995; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original score in pencil, undated (Box-folder MIL4-24)
  - Score, 1995 (Box-folder MIL4-24)
- 14: "Why Do the Angels Sing Tonight?" music by Don Miller, lyrics by Mildred Rapp, 1985; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Score, 1985 (Box-folder MIL4-25)
  - Review, 1985 (Box-folder MIL4-25)
- 15: "Down in Yon Forest" arrangement by Don Miller, undated, 2000; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Original score in pencil, n.d. (Box-folder MIL4-26)
  - Score, 2000 (Box-folder MIL4-26)
- 16: "Thanksgiving Canticle" arrangement by Don Miller, 1989 - 1990; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Score, 1989 - 1990 (Box-folder MIL4-27)
- 17: "Music From Around the World" by Don Miller, 2009; Miller, Donald B., 1937- (Box-folder 4-27A)
  - Musical score books for cello/bass, violin 1,2,3 and viola, 2009 (Box-folder MIL4-27A)
- 18: "Christmas Strings" by Don Miller, 2007; Miller, Donald B., 1937-
  - Score for Violin 1 & 2 with Piano accompaniment, 2007 (Box-folder MIL4-28)
  - Score for Cello and Bass with Piano accompaniment, 2007 (Box-folder MIL4-28)
  - Score for Viola, Violin and Ensemble, 2007 (Box-folder MIL4-28)
- 19: PhD Dissertation by Donald Miller, 1968 - 1980
  - Interviews of and about Kirke Mechem, 1971 - 1979 (Box-folder MIL6-1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Press Releases about Kirke Mechem, 1965 - 1984 (Box-folder MIL6-2)
  - Musical Programs of Kirke Mechem, 1960 - 1983 (Box-folder MIL6-3)
  - Symphony Preview Speeches by Kirke Mechem, 1965 - 1968 (Box-folder MIL6-4)
  - Journal Articles, April, 1970
    - "Choral Cycle" by Kirke Mechem, 1970 (Box-folder MIL6-5)
    - "Choral Music of Kirke Mechem" by Donald B. Miller, 1970 (Box-folder MIL6-6)
    - Articles for PhD thesis by various authors, 1960's - 1980's (Box MIL9)
  - Book: "I Could Hear the Least Bird Sing: Selected Poems" by Kirke Mechem, 1979 (Box-folder MIL6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1969 - 1981 and 2019; The bulk of the correspondence is between Donald B. Miller and Kirke Mechem. (Box-folder MIL6-8, MIL 3-14)
  - Photograph of Kirke Mechem, undated (Box-folder MIL6-9)
  - Scores by Kirke Mechem, 1954 - 1979 (Box MIL7-8)
  - Reel to Reel and cassette Recordings of Kirke Mechem's music, 1960's - 1980's (Box MIL3)
  - Draft of dissertation, undated (Box MIL7A)
- 20: Miscellaneous material, 1959 - 1983
  - Award placques, 1959 - 1966 (Box-folder MIL1-45)
  - Newspaper clipping, 1998 (Box-folder MIL1-44)
  - Examination - Qualifying examination in Church Music by Donald Miller, 1978 (Box-folder MIL1-43)
  - Article - Music History: 20 Topics by Donald Miller, 1983 (Box-folder MIL1-42)
  - Patent Registration Certificate, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Recordings of music by Donald Miller, 1960's - 1990's (Box 3, Box 5)
- 21: "Le Moyen Peu Frequente" by Donald B. Miller, undated
  - Original score in pencil, undated (Box 2)